# 大家好 我們剛從北京回來 都出差出了
Hi everyone! We're just back from Beijing. We had been on a business trip for a,
# 將近一個多禮拜啊
for almost a week.
# 你看 回來 這個魚缸都變成這樣子了
Look! Back home, the fish tank has already become this piece of mess.
# 還有幾條龍蝦
There are still some crayfish.
# 幸存者
The survivors
# 其他全沒啦
The rest are all gone.
# 你看 這個龍蝦
Look! This crayfish,
# 現在都 睡在地上 耍賴啊 它要 要離開這裡
They're all, lying on the ground, shamelessly. They wanna leave this place.
# 好啦 我回來了 給你接水了 現在就有水來了
Alright! I'm now back. I'm catching water for you. The water is coming right away.
# 現在管子掉子 沒沒了 這裡都乾了
Now the pipe is gone. Here's no more water and it's already dried out here.
# 魚也還有哦 還有幾條魚
There are still some fish, a couple of fish.
# 還活著
They survived.
# 到時條清洗一下
I'm gonna wash the tank later.
# 草就是長得 到處都是
And the weed is growing everywhere.
# 長滿了野草
The weed is everywhere.
# 你看 這個雞 雞鴨現在還在 那鵝也還在
Look! The chicks, the chicks and the ducks are still here, and the geese too.
# 我以為快餓扁了嘞 沒餓扁
I thought they were starved to death, but not yet.
# 又胖了
They get fat again.
# 全部過來啦 今天早上我餵了它們一下
They're all coming. I fed them something this morning.
# 這鴨子越來越漂亮啦
The ducks are getting prettier day by day,
# 這個鵝也是
and the geese too.
# 現在都沒那麼胖啦 都很結實
They're no longer that fat now, and are really firm instead.
# 誒 那公雞 那公雞
Ey? The rooster, the rooster,
# 公雞跑哪裡去了
where has the rooster fled to?
# 你看 這箱蜜蜂好像也跑了
Look! The bees in the box seem to have run away too.
# 沒蜂蜜了
There's no more honey,
# 都沒蜜蜂了 (註︰他經常把「蜂蜜」和「蜜蜂」說錯，這裡稍為配合一下)
no more honey bees.
# 不知道跑哪裡去了
I wonder where they are now.
# 還有蜂蜜
Here's still some honey.
# 哦 還有一點點
Oh? Here's still a tiny little bit.
# 它們肯定這兩天跑了
They must have run away in this couple of days.
# 看到我不在了
They ran away,
# 看到我不在這裡它就跑了
ran away, seeing that I was not here.
# 等下它們 不知道它們會不會到這裡來
I wonder, who knows if they're coming back here.
# 你看 這個象草那麼高啦
Look! The elephant grass is that tall now.
# 給(註︰我聽到「割」)點給鵝吃 看它吃不吃
Let me cut some for the geese, and see if they like it.
# 那麼嫩
It's so tender.
# 它們看到都怕
The presence is already enough to scare them.
# 來都不來 不吃象草
They're not even coming. They don't like elephant grass.
# 你看 這個
Look! This is,
# 這個果子全熟啦
these fruits are all ripe now.
# 像藍莓一樣
They're like blueberries.
# 有種怪怪的味道
There's a funny taste.
# 可能我口味比較重
Perhaps because of my preference to strong tastes,
# 我們吃不下 我怎麼覺得那麼好吃
it tastes somehow rather nice to me. But they all can't stand it.
# 還小的時候我們吃了好多這個
I ate a lot of this stuff when I was a kid.
# 好啦 不能吃那麼多
Alright! More doesn't always mean better.
# 好 我下去把那個草先割一下這個草
Good! I'm going down there and have the weed, and clear the weed first.
# 到處都是那個野草都長滿了
Everywhere is the weed. It's growing,
# 長滿了那個野草
growing everywhere.
# 我們走的時候
By the time we left,
# 就那麼高一點點 現在都那麼高啦
they reached not higher than this. But they have become that tall now,
# 才一個禮拜
in just one week.
# 長得好快的 很茂盛
They grow really fast, and very well.
# 這個葉子
The leaves,
# 營養很豐富的
are very nutritious.
# 下次我去兄弟家牽一頭羊回來
Next time I'll take a goat here, from my buddy's place.
# 給它吃一下
Let it have a try,
# 嘗一下這里的味道
try the flavour here.
# 很好吃的哦
It's really tasty, you know.
# 你看 這紫色的也是長得那麼漂亮啦
Look! The violet ones are also so pretty now.
# 你看這個攀蒲 這是攝影小哥奶奶種的哦
Have a look at the "panpu" (pumpkins). They were planted by Mr. Cameraman's grandma.
# 我們走的時候只有
By the time we left, they were only,
# 只有 只有三十公分左右
only, only about thirty centimetres.
# 現在 現在都
Now, now they're,
# 三四米啦
already three or four metres.
# 長得好快呀
They grow really fast.
# 這草
The weed...
# 這個攀蒲一個都可以長二三十斤哦
The "panpu" can be up to ten to fifteen kilograms each.
# 把肥料搞好來
If they're well fertilised,
# 就可以長
they can even,
# 長個四五十斤都有可能長得出來
even be up to twenty or twenty five kilograms.
# 到時候我們就有攀蒲吃啦
We'll have panpu by that time.
# 太高啦
It's too tall!
# 這草長得好快的
The weed is growing really fast.
# 看一下西瓜
Let's have a look at the watermelons.
# 西瓜在這上面
The watermelons are up there.
# 你看這個西瓜
Look! The watermelons,
# 我走的時候就那麼長一點 現在都那麼長啦
By the time I left, they were not longer than this. But they're that long now.
# 長得好快啊
They grow really fast.
# 那邊還有
More over there
# 這個西瓜長那麼長啦
This watermelon, is that long now.
# 還有一個百香果
And here's a passion fruit.
# 啊 這個百香果 草都那麼
Ah! This passion fruit, the weed is so,
# 那麼長
so long!
# 你看這個薑
Have a look at the ginger!
# 上次我們走的時候都還沒出來
They were still under the earth when we left.
# 你看現在長那麼快
Look! They're growing so fast now.
# 全出來了
They've all come out.
# 長得好快啊
They grow really fast.
# 這邊也是
This side too
# 就一點點
Just a tiny little bit
# 你看這個西紅杮
Have a look at the tomatoes!
# 這是豬種的哦 那條大公豬 那些小豬 跟大豬
They were planted by the pigs, I mean that big boar and those piggies, and the big ones.
# 一起種的西紅杮
They planted the tomatoes together.
# 現在長那麼茂盛啦
They're growing so well now.
# 到時我們就可以摘啦
We can pick them later.
# 現在我們插播一個小廣告
Now we're embedding an advertisement here.
# 你看 這個就是我們逢年過節都會吃的 這個月亮巴
Look! This is a snack that we all enjoy during festivals and celebrations. It's called "yue liang ba" (lit: moon crust)
# 我們土話叫 **** (註︰這真是原字幕的寫法，翻譯的注音由胡跃清提供)
In our native dialect, it's called "toukuolazi" (note: untranslatable).
# 你看 有黃豆的 有花生的
Look! Some are with soybeans, some are with peanuts.
# 逢年過節都會做點來吃
They always have a place on the table during festivals and celebrations.
# 現在你看 這個包裝還可以哦
And now, look! The packaging is not bad.
# 它的優點就是
The plus is,
# 很好吃
that it's really tasty.
# 缺點 就是吃多了會上火
The minus is, that eating too many may give you a sore throat.
# 給大家看一下 這個
Let me show you, this is,
# 不怎麼油膩哦
it's not that oily.
# 是烤出來的
Cuz it's roasted.
# 很香
It smells really good!
# 肚子餓了 可以吃一點
You can have some, whenever you're hungry.
# 特別是去 去外面玩的時候 多帶點這個
Especially when you're having an outing, taking more of this snack with you,
# 可以充饑
can alleviate your hunger.
# 好啦 我們去看一下那個小狗
Alright! Let's have a look at the doggies.
# 你看 大公豬回來啦
Look! The big boar is back.
# 來
C'mon!
# 吃點這個
Eat some!
# 搞了一點點飼料給它們 兩下就吃光啦
I've fetched them a tiny little bit of fodder. They finished everything in just a second.
# 看來它肚子真的餓啦
It seems that it's really hungry.
# 你看它的豬耳朵
Have a look at its pig ears.
# 它的豬耳朵肯定好吃
Its pig eats must be very tasty.
# 這個肉 我再去摘點飼料給它
The pork... I'm gonna fetch more fodder.
# 你看 現在好溫順啊
Look! It's so nice and gentle now.
# 走開先 走開先 等一下來
Go 'way, go 'way first. It's not yet your turn.
# 這狗在這裡
The dog is here,
# 想要我安慰它一樣
he seems to be asking for my comfort.
# 老是伸 把脖子伸過來
He keeps on stretch, stretching his neck towards me.
# 想要我給它按摩
He wants me to give him a massage.
# 好啦好啦好啦
Alright, alright, alright!
# 誒呦
Eyo?
# 弄痛你啦
Did I hurt you?
# 下去一點
Get away a bit!
# 哇 這個毛
Wa! The hair,
# 好 好硬啊
is so, so stiff.
# 再去搞點給你吃
I'm gonna give you more.
# 這個母狗
This mother,
# 三年多啦
is more than three years old.
# 它的子孫後代都不知道有多少 我都數不出來啦
She now has countless children and grand children. I've already lost the count.
# 你的毛怎麼這樣子啦 你又不胖啦
What happened to your coat? You're not chubby anymore.
# 過兩天我帶你去洗澡 去不去
Let me take you to have a bath a few days later, shall I?
# 誒呀 站一站 我看一下你身上
Eya! Stand up! Let me have a look at your body.
# 變成這樣子啦
You've changed so much!
# 跑到我老家來啦
It comes to my home.
# 這裡種了幾個桃樹哦
I've planted some peach trees here,
# 就在我家門口
right in front of my door.
# 到時候有桃子的時候我就把它做個籬笆 把它圍起來
When there are peaches, I'll, I'll make a fence, and fence up this area.
# 多好啊
So nice!
# 現在還小 這個桃樹
They're still small, the peach trees.
# 你看 那個雞
Look at that chicken.
# 專吃草的 太壞啦
It eats grass, and only grass. Bad guy!
# 這個放 以前種了那個草皮的哦
Here's tur, here used to be turfed, you know.
# 現在被它吃成這樣子啦
But it looks like this now, because of the chicken.
# 到時候要把雞關起來 不能把它放出來啦
I'll lock up all the chicks later. They shouldn't be allowed to run around.
# 帶到下面 帶到下面去養
I'll bring them down there, keep them down there.
# 不要走哦
Don't run away.
# 以前跟著豬混
He loved mingling with the pigs.
# 現在跟豬混不下去啦
But now he can no longer mingle with the pigs.
# 就跟我混啦
So he mingles with me.
# 是不是
Am I right?
# 豬都不給你東西吃
The pigs were not giving you any food.
# 它也不割點肉給你吃哦
They didn't cut their pork for you.
# 看一下 我經常給肉給你吃
Have a look! I always give you meat.
# 我是經常給豬肉給你吃哦
I always give you pork, right?
# 現在都
He's now,
# 很聽話啦
a very good boy.
# 你看 看一捏它它就 享受 (註︰這裡的享受是多了)
Look! Once I start pinching him, he,
# 享受
he enjoys.
# 看到沒有
See?
# 跟它
I give him a,
# 頸椎按 (註︰我好像聽到「脊椎」)
a spinal mass,
# 頸椎按摩
spinal massage,
# 脖子按摩啊
a neck massage.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.